He's declared a unilateral retreat and
defeat in this new cold war. He's
pulling us out. And instead of this
United States contending with other two
powers and maneuvering and maximizing
its alliances and its diplomacy and its
economic leverage uh to maintain some
kind of stable balance [music] like we
did during the cold war and its
aftermath, he's pulling out completely
and he's got a kind of different very
different vision, a kind of trontinental
vision.
Welcome back to another episode of Deep
Focus. If you followed the news lately,
and I know you do, [music] we all do,
uh, you know all about the US uh,
rattling the the cage of Iran. You know
about the the snatching of Venezuelan
President Maduro. You know about the
whole Greenland story. And you probably
know that China is doing so well
financially that it's just buying
alliances all over the world. Well, does
this spell the end of the US empire? Are
we in those final years or maybe final
decades of the US empire? After all, we
can't maintain this defense budget
forever.
One trillion dollars. Donald Trump wants
to raise it to one half trillion
dollars. Remember at today's budget
that's bigger than the next eight
largest countries in the world combined.
I travel a lot. I see the the kinds of
roads that other countries have, the the
first class hospitals, the beautiful
airports, the ports,
high-speed bullet trains. Why don't we
have those things? Well, because we
spend our money on war and on the
implements of war. We're going to talk
about that and about what the future
holds with a renowned expert in this
area. Professor Alfred uh McCoy is an
American historian and he's an educator.
He is a professor at the University of
Wisconsin at Madison and he is
extensively published on the issue of of
American hegemony. He's also an expert
in the history of the Philippines, the
foreign policy of the United States,
European colonization of Southeastern
Europe, Southeast Asia, rather, the
illegal international drug trade, and
the CIA's history of covert operations.
We could have a whole conversation just
about that. Professor McCoy, thanks so
much for joining us. It's great to have
you,
>> John. Pleasure being on.
>> So, Professor, you've argued um you've
been very consistent in your arguments
over the course of decades. uh you've
argued recently in in a new book uh in
uh an interview with Democracy Now on
Tom Dispatch uh and elsewhere that we
really are in the final stages of of the
end of the American Empire. Can you
explain that to us? Can you walk us
through it and and how we got to what
appears to be the beginning of the end
rather quickly compared to other
empires?
>> Sure. Uh [clears throat]
let me begin at the beginning. I'm an
historian of the Philippines. Actually,
more particularly, I'm an historian of
parts of two little islands. Not so
little, but you know, from a global
perspective, two little islands in the
Philippines. All right. So, so how do I
know about the whole big wide world or
what right do I have to say about
anything? Well, uh, about 21 years ago,
I got together with 130 historians on
three continents who were experts in
various aspects of imperial history, and
we mounted a project on empires in
transition. We looked to the European
past, the American present, and the
global future. and we held conferences
in Madison, Wisconsin, Sydney,
Australia, Manila, Philippines, and
Barcelona, Spain. We published two books
which together are about 1,500
pages long. and and what we came up to
at that time when we wrapped up the
project in about 2011 2012 after 8 years
a pretty hard work a lot of you know
footnotes and cogitation what we came up
to is that it looked like the United
States Empire was following the course
of all empires they rise they peak they
decline it's just inevitable and it
looked like the United States was
clearly on a trajectory of decline what
was missing by about 2012 when we were
wrapping up our affairs was really a
successor power
>> and [clears throat] it was just at that
point that China was coming online. And
the United States admitted in one of the
great errors in the history of empires,
the United States thought that it could
bring China with 20% of the world's
population and the most powerful uh
empire consistently throughout human
history. we can bring this this little
state China into the World Trade
Organization into the international
trading community and then we could
somehow make them play the game by our
rules, right? You know, because I don't
know because we're so powerful and or or
we're so nice or we're I don't know
whatever it was. It was just a an an
incredible exercise of imperial hubris
by elites in Washington DC. And by the
time China had spent a decade inside the
World Trade Organization, they had
accumulated $4 trillion dollar in
foreign exchange surplus. And in 2013,
President Xiinping launched China on the
Belt and Road initiative, which is the
largest foreign aid and development and
loan program in the history of
humankind. It's 10 times 10 times the
size of the Marshall Plan which up to
that point at during at the end of at
the start of the Cold War 1947 to 48 to
1952 it was 13 billion. It was the
biggest foreign aid program in human
history. It was incredibly successful.
Well, the Belt and Road Initiative was
10 times the foreign aid program and it
launched China on a trajectory towards
global power. And so suddenly beginning
in 2012 2013 we were looking for a
successor power some nation strong
enough powerful enough to challenge
America and that has been China. And you
know I've been in my little way
following China following this game of
empires since then. So it's been
basically 21 years that I've been
working on this project. And I got some
observations that I can share with you
if you
>> I' I'd love to hear them.
>> Okay. Look, as I said earlier, all
empires have a natural cycle. They rise,
they peak, they decline. And and clearly
by 2004, the United States was on the
decline. I mean, you could see it. I
mean, good heavens, the Imperial hubris,
the, you know, the invasion of Iraq in
2000, uh, 2003,
uh, based on on bogus fabricated
intelligence about weapons of mass
destruction and the dismal outcome of
that, the simultaneous intervention in
Afghanistan, which is a 20-year path to
disaster. Okay, both of them in a global
scale, you know, medium-siz events, but
indicative of an empire that was in
decline. At the start of the Cold War,
whenever we intervened with just the
breath, the hint of US intervention,
governments fell, uh, presidents fled
into exile and our clients took power in
in prime ministerships and presidential
palaces around the world. Well, clearly
that age was over. There all kinds of
signs of decline. Okay. uh and so uh the
the question then is you know in this
natural trajectory to decline how is the
US managing this decline how is it
dealing with its descent from being you
know the world's sole superpower a
unipolar power into being primis
interaris okay uh it can be done look at
the United Kingdom okay United Kingdom
during its century plus of global
Dominion acquired enough cultural,
intellectual, and financial assets so
that it's declined from controlling a
quarter of the globe directly and half
of the planet both directly and
indirectly to being a, you know, a
modest island, you know, off the coast
of Europe. um you know it's been
softened by the accumulated assets
cultural, financial, political that
Britain acquired in at its peak of
power. So we could have done the same.
We could have had a a long slow
trajectory where we lose elements of our
hegemony, but the world system that
we've created and that and that we would
continue to defend would provide us with
you kind of a buffer with assets that we
could carry for into our retirement. if
you will, from uh from global hegemony.
Well, it's not worked out that way. Um
uh
the the Trump administration is is
adopted very aggressive policies uh in
several related arenas that are
accelerating that decline. And if I
could go through them very quickly, um
the first is geopolitics. All right,
this is the the underpinning of all
global power. It's a word that's thrown
around in the newspapers and magazines
among the the commentary at you know
very glibly but it's actually you know a
serious subject and when you look at
geopolitics from an academic perspective
uh you reach a conclusion that for a
thousand years more or less and
certainly for the last 500 years the
basis of global hegemony is a dominant
position on the Eurasian landmass.
From a geopolitical perspective, Eurasia
is by far the biggest continent
on the planet, it's home to 70% 70% of
the world's population and productivity.
Seven out of every 10 people on the
planet live in Eurasia. All right? So to
be a contending or hegemonic power, you
have to have a presence in Eurasia. The
United States uh learned this during
World War II. After all, what was that
war fought all about? Why why did those
77 million people die? Because the
United States was fighting to evict the
Axis powers from their perch at the
antipodess, the axial ends of Eurasia,
Japan in the east, Nazi Germany and
Italy in the west. Okay? And when we
done when we did that, we took those
positions. We were the we were dominant
in Western Europe and we occupied Japan
and South Korea etc. Okay. And so at the
start of the cold war, you know, that
founding generation that launches the
cold war, those guys were most of them
ex-military guys like Dwight Eisenhower.
They were men who during World War II
for four years, they had drunk a daily
diet of geopolitics between their
morning coffee and their bourbon night
caps. They knew exactly where global
power lay and they created the US
position at the start of the cold war at
both ends the antipodess of the Eurasian
landmass that made us exceptionally
strong and we ring that continent with
bands of steel in terms of mutual
security alliances very importantly NATO
uh MTO STO and then f those are middle
eastern Southeast Asian packs okay mito
from basically uh from Turkey all the
way to Pakistan and Sito from Pakistan
all the way to the Philippines and then
five bilateral
mutual defense packs up the Pacific
literal from Australia, the Philippines,
Taiwan, South Korea, Japan. We ringed
Eurasia. We were dominant. We confined
the Soviet Union, the Sinos Soviet block
behind the Iron Curtain. And whenever
they ventured out, we often sent covert
operatives to check their interventions.
Sometimes we sent conventional forces as
we did in South Korea, uh, South
Vietnam. Um, uh, uh, okay. But we
managed always to kind of push them back
behind the iron curtain and keep them
contained, giving us the free world,
threequarters of the planet for our
ambit during the cold war. And all we
had, all Washington did during the cold
war, our basic strategy is keep them
contained and then wait for them to make
a mistake. And of course in 1979, they
ventured out. Okay? They invaded and
occupied Afghanistan because the local
their local communist clients were not
doing well. They sent 100,000 troops.
What did America do? He sent one guy,
you know, CI operative, ven veteran CIA
guy, Howard Hart, sent him to and he,
you know, used CIA's millions. He built
a a mujadin Afghani army of 250,000 men.
And for 10 years, we the Mujadin
bloodied and beat the Soviet army. And
when they pulled out in February of
1989, they were demoralized. They were a
hollow shell. And within months, you
know, because remember February 1989,
the last Soviet tanks come across the
Friendship Bridge from Afghanistan into
the then Soviet Union. And you know,
that's February. Eight, nine months
later, Eastern Europe erupts in mass
protests, anti-communist protests,
challenging overthrowing Soviet client
states in the captive nations of Eastern
Europe, the critical buffer zone that
Stalin created and grabbed at the end of
World War II. And you know every time
before that when the mobs in uh arose to
protest the crowds arose to protest
communism Eastern Europe the Warsaw pack
sent the tanks 1956 Hungary they sent
thousands of tanks to crush that
uprising. Uh in 1968 in the Prague
spring they sent tanks into Prague crush
that uprising. This time they didn't
send tanks. Well, actually they sent a
few in Lithuania and that didn't go well
and the protests kept erupting until
there was actually a massive protest
against that Lithuanian intervention in
Moscow itself by a 100,000 Russians
protesting Soviet intervention. I mean
basically the satellite states broke
free and the Soviet Union broke up and
the cold war was over and America's
geopolitical strategy had proven to be
ruthlessly but brilliantly successful.
Uh, I mean it was a great victory in
basically the longest war in modern
history. In fact, the longest war
probably in history, longest major war
in human history. Okay, we won hands
down because we had a skillful
geopolitical strategy and we maintain
that position. Okay, in the decades
since, well, what is President Donald
Trump doing? Donald Trump has decided
that he's going to pursue something
different. Instead of the United States
being a global hedgeimon contending for
power in the Eurasian land mass in what
scholars have called the new cold war
between Moscow, Beijing, and Washington,
he's declared a unilateral retreat and
defeat in this new cold war. He's
pulling us out. And instead of this
United States contending with other two
powers and maneuvering and maximizing
its alliances and its diplomacy and its
economic leverage uh to maintain some
kind of stable balance like we did
during the cold war and its aftermath,
he's pulling out completely and he's got
a kind of different very different
vision, a kind of trontinental vision.
>> Well, may I may I interrupt you on that
point? Over the last several weeks,
there have been a couple of pieces in
places like the Wall Street Journal, the
New York Times, the Washington Post to a
lesser extent, but they they talked
about using the Maduro uh snatching as
as a hook. They said that Trump has
reiterated
uh the Monroe Doctrine that there will
be no foreign interventions, no Chinese
refineries in the Western Hemisphere,
etc., etc. But at the same time, they
argued he was conceding Taiwan to the
Chinese and conceding Ukraine to the
Russians and he was pulling us back into
a multipolar world or into acceptance of
a multipolar world. Do you think it's
been that well thought out? Or perhaps
Trump is seeing the the writing on the
wall on the one hand that we are near
the end of our empire. But even if
that's true, how do we account for this
crazy proposal to increase the Pentagon
budget by 50%.
>> Okay, couple things. First of all, you
talked about um Ukraine, Venezuela,
Taiwan. Okay, the the current chips on
the on the the risk board of
geopolitics. Okay, that all fits with
with with Trump's strategy, which I call
his trontinental strategy. Instead of
the US being a global hedgeimon
contending uh for its you know on the
Eurasian land mass and competing with
other powers, what he sees instead is
basically the world the partition of the
planet in three zones with Russia under
Putin dominant in the former Soviet
sphere places like Ukraine. Uh and then
China dominant in East Asia. Uh so give
them Taiwan, who cares? Uh and then the
United States and and Trump states this
very expressly, very explicitly in the
national security strategy which he
released last November that the United
States will become dominant in the
Western Hemisphere and this will become
our zone and we will exercise our full
military, commercial and diplomatic
leverage to maintain our hegemonic
control over this region. And you know I
I think it's uh ill advised in a couple
of ways. First of all, a unilateral
retreat and a self-inflicted defeat in
in the great game of nations pulling
back from uh Eurasia and withdrawing
from global contention uh is going to be
very destabilizing for the world. It
will certainly weaken the US position
not only diplomatic and and militarily
but also economically and we can come to
that later on. Okay. But second of all,
this retreat into the Americas and this
attempt to create a US sphere in the
Americas is not going to play well in
Latin America. We did this from the
1890s through the early 1930s. It was
called gunboat diplomacy. Uh we, you
know, intervened
in Colombia. We presided over the
independence of Panama and then with
unseammly haste we grabbed the Panama
Canal zone in a treaty with the client
government that we virtually created. We
shunted forces in and out of countries
like the Dominican Republic, Haiti,
Nicaragua. They stayed for years,
sometimes decades for at a time, turned
them into virtual client states and
aroused such antipathy in Latin America
that when President Roosevelt took
office in 19 President Franklin Delano
Roosevelt, FDR took office in 1933, one
of the first things he did was to
proclaim a good neighbor policy with
Latin America, which was a basically
kind of like a an indirect apology for
what we've been up to and a promise that
we would be intervening in Latin America
again. And this paid huge benefits
during World War II uh despite Nazi
attempts to in Vagel and and uh with
conservative governments in Latin
America, it maintained a a loyal
pro-American zone. We had a very strong
ally in Brazil that was critical for our
geopolitical position. World War II.
After the war, uh we signed the Rio
Pact. Most people don't even know the
Rio pact anymore, but it's still there.
It is a mutual defense treaty for most
of the nations in the Western
Hemisphere, you know, signed as peers,
as equals. We're going to defend each
other. All right. Um, and then in 1955,
very importantly, we concluded the NORAD
agreement with Canada, which is the
closest military alliance on the planet,
bar none. I mean, most Americans don't
even know there is a NORAD. NORAD has
been critical to our defense since 1955.
It's how we defend our our northern
frontier. The under NORAD, the commander
is an American Air Force officer. The
deputy commander is a Canadian. And so
we have a foreigner, a non-American
actually in command of American forces.
I mean, this is extraordinary. There's
no other alliance like it in the world
today. Uh not even NATO comes close to
the intimacy of that. So, so we were in
a very strong position in this
hemisphere and this exercise of this
unilateral great power susanity over the
Americas is is already backfiring. Mark
Carney, Prime Minister of Canada, a very
intelligent and very skillful leader,
off to Beijing recently, concluding a
ending the the the kind of coolness in
relations, signing a what looks to be
like an important economic relationship
with China. The Latin American region,
which chafed mightily during the era of
gunboat diplomacy, uh has its
nationalism just beneath the surface,
ready to erupt. This is a very strong
region of nationalism Latin America. Uh
and and [clears throat] you know uh
let's let's put it bluntly. Okay, look
armies, navies, air forces, military
does not an empire make. Okay, it's an
instrument. It's a tool.
Trump has confused the the tools, the
toys with the geopolitical reality.
Okay. The real substance of empire is is
diplomatic alliances and close
commercial relations. China is already
the dominant economic power in Latin
America. Nothing Trump has done is going
to change that and and and can change
that. Okay. If anything, uh I mean look
what happened. you know, his
announcement that Canada is going to
become the 51st state, you know, um,
again, offending Canadian nationalism,
which is a more subtle nationalism, you
know, way deeper beneath the skin than
Latin American nationalism. But even
that just recoiled, rebelled, and, you
know, Canada's off on its own middle
power path. And that, you know, and that
includes cozing up to China. Well, that
that's already been going on in Latin
America and that can intensify, you
know, uh and and the consequences will
be that at the ironically Trump attempts
to claim, you know, the Americas as our
sphere and the process of claiming it
accelerates the loss. So, in other
words, when you think about it
geopolitically, we're withdrawing from
Eurasia, uh weakening the NATO alliance
by the grab for Greenland, uh uh maybe
even not just crippling but ultimately
killing the NATO alliance. Okay. Um
weakening the alliance with our Asian
allies to to retreat into the Americas
and in the process alienating, you know,
uh once close allies in the Americas,
winding up with pretty much not much at
all. uh so that that geopolitically
that's one element of the mismanagement
of the US geopolitical position and and
that there there are other uh other
complimenting and corresponding factors
we can talk about
>> before we go on I want to take a short
break and tell you when I was a kid my
grandfather handed me a silver coin
seriously a 1921 silver dollar I still
have it and he said to me this is real
money I didn't really understand it then
but I never forgot the weight of it in
my hand. It felt different. It was
solid. It was permanent. It was honest.
Years later, after watching inflation
just eat away savings and hearing
politicians spin stories that don't
really match reality, it finally
clicked. That coin didn't just hold
value. It taught me what real value
feels like. Well, these days, gold has
blown past $5,000 an ounce. Many people
missed it. But silver may be about to do
what it almost always does next. Catch
up and move faster. Silver isn't just a
store of value. It's essential. It's
everywhere. It's in solar panels,
electric vehicles, cell phones, medical
technology, and once it's used, it's
gone. A new free report breaks this all
down. It's called the silver surge and
it shows why this so-called people's
medal could be one of the biggest wealth
opportunities of the decade. You can go
to johnloves.com
to get this free report. You could also
call 888 gold053.
That's 888 gold053
and johnloves.com.
help me understand the the thought
process as the at the White House visav
Iran.
I think I think everything that you've
laid out is exactly what we're seeing
happening before our eyes. Uh we likely
are at the end of the empire. We likely
are trying to reiterate American uh
primacy uh over the Western Hemisphere
while conceding other areas to the
world's other powers. But what about
Iran? The Iranians aren't a threat to
the United States. They they may be to
Israel just as much as Israel is a
threat to Iran. So why would we even
play with the idea of of yet another war
of choice? We're we're filming this on
uh February the 4th and about two hours
ago, President Trump issued a statement
that Ayatollah Kamay better watch out.
Well, what are we supposed to take from
that? And and how how would it be in US
interests to launch yet another war of
choice, especially against a a country
as big and as populous as Iran without
international support?
Um, it's not just Trump that harbors
this illusion of the importance of the
Middle East. It's the neocons, the
neoconservatives of which he was
initially kind of a dissident but has
more or less kind of, if you will,
stolen their thunder, appropriated their
policy, and has in office has kind of
fit in their groove. All right. Um uh
essentially the neoconservatives took us
into war in in in Iraq uh because it was
deemed to be the way we would uh get
ourselves a bastion sight ourselves in
Iraq uh and uh disseminate democracy
capitalism and take fuller control over
the region's vast oil reserves. Okay.
And Donald Trump is a man who's equates
economics with minerals of various
sorts. He's made that pretty clear. All
right. uh you know Greenland is
minerals, Ukraine is minerals,
everything is minerals and the Middle
East is oil and Venezuela is oil. Okay.
Uh so [clears throat] uh and among the
various minerals I suppose if you had to
say Donald Trump's favorite min mineral
is oil. He thinks oil is power. All
right. And indeed it was but it no
longer is. And so he's attaching us uh
to it' be like in 1950
if we invaded England because we wanted
to get their coal reserves. Okay? Just
at the moment that coal was no longer
the prime US source of of energy. Okay?
And and and this brings us to the second
uh mistake that the Trump administration
is making. The second major policy
decision that is accelerating US
decline. Okay. Would you mind John if I
played history professor for a second?
Okay. Because that's what I do history.
Okay. When you look over the last the
history of empires over the last 500
years, right? And not every historian
agrees with me and this is my own take
on things, but I think it's a reasonable
argument. Okay. The rise of every global
hedgeimon over the last 500 years has
been synonymous with and caused by their
mastery of new forms of of energy. Okay.
So with the Iberians, Spain and
Portugal, what they discovered was that
by the capturing of Africans and
enslaving them and working them to
beyond
to the brink of death and beyond and
working them in tropical clims. Northern
Europe was agriculture 6 months a year.
In the tropics, you can work 12 months a
year. So you could work the human body
to the point of death. And indeed on
most plantations in the Caribbean was
about a 15% death rate. Young healthy
African males work to death you know in
a matter of three four five years. Okay.
So maximization of energy output from
the human body builds these great
empires. Okay. Then along come the next
ascended power the Dutch. The Dutch a
very poor region devoid of natural
resources but you know very windy and
they got windmills now. And they're not
just cute little things. Okay. The Zhan
district near Amsterdam was the world's
first industrial zone. And there there
were 150 windmills that could turn tree
trunks into smooth uniform planks at the
rate of 60 trunks a day per per
windmill. Okay, this was a this allowed
the the cheap production of the world's
fastest ships that were the most
efficient. And by riding the winds, the
Dutch built an empire that stretched
from uh the spice islands of Indonesia
to Manhattan. Okay. And then along come
the British who uh succeeded the Dutch
and they in the late 18th century James
Watt invents the the steam engine. The
British then over the next 40 years make
micro version of steam engines. They put
it on trains to make the railroads in
the 1820s. The Royal Navy puts them on
ships in the 1840s. They come up with
tools that will sculpt the earth's
surface. The steam shovel, the steam
roller, the steam dredge. Okay? And this
propels Britain to global power in
control of a colonial empire that rules
over a quarter of humanity. Okay? And
then uh in the United States uh by 1950,
we're replacing coal with oil. And oil
is synonymous with American
civilization, American power. But it's
over. Right now, we are in the midst of
something that is akin to the industrial
revolution, the age of steam and steel,
the the creation of alternative energy
that and and China is writing this green
energy revolution to global power. And
just as the United States is withdrawing
from the Eurasian land mass and
inflicting a geopolitical defeat on
itself, so the Trump administration is
using the very formidable powers of the
American presidency to destroy to to to
strangle America's infant energy
revolution in its cradle. Okay? Denying
construction permits for wind farms off
the Atlantic coast.
O opening up coal fields, opening up oil
drilling, abolishing the uh $7,500 tax
credit that was going to allow Detroit
to make a a transition to to electric
vehicles. All right? And and China is
doing the exact opposite. China is
lending its full economic resources and
the considerable resources of the
Chinese state to the construction of
this green energy revolution. they
already produce 70% plus of the world's
world's solar panels and solar
components. All right.
>> [clears throat]
>> uh they produce a similar amount 70% of
the world's electrical vehicles and they
are presiding and this has happened so
fast within the last four to five years
China's auto industry has gone from
basically a joke okay they couldn't even
sell their own cars in their own country
right okay and now they're producing
these absolutely state-of-the-art
electrical vehicles China has electrical
vehicles that solve all the problems uh
uh Chinese latest batteries, they charge
in 5 minutes. Uh the the the loss of
battery power to cold, that's gone. Uh
the distance uh Chinese has standard
production batteries that have a 600
mile distance on a single charge. And
you can buy a Chinese subcompact
electrical vehicle self-driving for
$9,000.
I mean, last time I looked, I couldn't
buy a 2010 Honda Civic with 150,000
miles on the clock for 9,000 bucks. I
mean, it's just amazing. And then
they've got they've got these robotic
factories that are enormous, biggest
some of the biggest factories in the
world that are cranking out these cars
literally by the millions where they go
to ports where they get loaded onto
specially designed ships. I I have to
tell you, I I went to China two years
ago for the very first time and I saw
these gorgeous cars that with and the
logo said BYD. I said, "What in the
world kind of car is this?" And my host
said, "Oh, that's beyond your dreams." I
said, "What the heck is that?" He said,
"It's the Chinese electric vehicle." I
said, "It's gorgeous. It It looks like
an Audi, like a very sporty Audi. Are
they expensive?" He said, "No, they're
about $18,000."
And I said, "Why have I never heard of
this car?" And he said, "Because the
United States is the only country where
they're not available. The only one." I
did some research and it turns out that
we've we've banned them effectively. Not
really. We've banned them by by putting
something like a a 250% tariff on these
Chinese electric vehicles. Now, with
this new deal that the Chinese have
negotiated with the the Canadians,
they're freely available in Canada. And
you're right about that battery. It
doesn't lose power in the cold and it
can go 600 miles. That's something that
American electric car batteries can't
do.
>> But just pretending that the problem
doesn't exist or that we can sanction it
or tariff it away, I think, is is very
shortsighted and just plain wrong. Well,
the president of Ford Motor pointed out,
I think, and I may have these stats
slightly wrong. He said that, "Look,
I've got 12,000 dealerships around the
world." And I think he said something
like 2,000 of them are in the United
States. In other words, the big three,
General Motors, Ford, Stalantis, they
sell more cars out of the United States
than they do in the United States,
right? They've got to compete in the
global market to survive. And if they
can't produce a competitive electrical
vehicle, within 5 years, they're all
going to be bankrupt. They're going to
be dead as doornails. Okay, it's just a
fact because one thing, okay, think
about it. The internal combustion
engine, the gas guzzler, right? When was
the last time there was a breakthrough
in anything anything in gas guzzling
technology? You know,
>> it's been a very very long time
>> about the la I don't know 1975
or something. I don't know. I mean, but
and yet, you know, the one thing about
the you know, all electrical vehicles
are is a steel box with a battery. And
so the technology they're engineers
working around the world and they're
making breakthroughs in this technology
we have not realized the potential of
the electric battery. All right. And the
other aspect of electrical batteries too
is as the the technology improves driven
by the automobile industry then we're
also getting new technologies for
storage batteries. So that when you look
at wind farms and solar power, the
weakness they have is the, you know, and
every
fossil fuel advocate says, "Oh, yeah,
sure, wind farms are cheap." Uh, you
know, uh, solar panels are cheap, right?
Right now, the the cost of generating
electricity in a solar panel is 40% of
the cost of the cheapest fossil fuel
component. The problem is, of course,
erratic nature. Sun only shines half the
day. uh wind doesn't blow all the time
etc. So you need storage batteries and
what's happening is that as the
batteries become cheaper and more
efficient all right then the capacity
for storage batteries. So what we're
looking at is a is a multiaceted
revolution in green energy with
electrical generation via solar and wind
backed up by electrical storage
batteries low cost high efficient that
even out the erratic nature of the of
the of the electrical generation and
then mobility through electrical
vehicles of all sorts. Uh, I'd say we're
no more than 10 years away from
America's truck fleet being all
electrical and all self-driving down
every interstate in America. Okay. uh
[clears throat] and and you know uh
this is going to be the products of
essentially foreign predominantly maybe
even exclusively Chinese
factories for both the the batteries the
the solar the wind and the motor
vehicles and
>> that's right
>> and if we lose if we lose Detroit okay
uh that's 3% of GDP last time I looked
there are 13 million American workers in
the automobile deal industry. It's the
biggest manufacturing industry in the
United States, bar none. You know, we
can't what that's going to do to the
quality of life in this country is going
to be really serious. And and and you
know, and so [clears throat] that's a
case where Trump's domestic policy, his
hostility towards alternative energy has
global ramifications. All right.
Absolutely global ramifications. And
another one is Trump's trade war. Okay.
That's the third strand in America's
decline. Um Trump uh uh has declared war
on not only allies and competitors but
indeed the entire international
uh economic order. You know at the start
of the cold war the end of World War II
and the start of the cold war the United
States presided over the creation of an
international order. We created the
United Nations. We virtually wrote the
charter with other nations
collaborating, but we did it in San
Francisco. And um then our our one of
our our third com our our next major
component after the United Nations was
something called the General Agreement
on Trade and Tariffs in 1947. That's
today the World Trade Organization. And
that basically I mean the the the the
[clears throat]
other component of the international
economic order was done at the towards
the end of World War II at Breton Woods
in 1944 that created the international
monetary fund. So the international
monetary fund regulated currencies and
currency exchange uh and the general
agreement on trades and tariffs. Now the
World Trade Organization set the rules
for world trade and as a result
[clears throat] uh the average tariff
among major trading partners went down
from about 22% in 1945 to about 2% when
Trump took office and he's now raised uh
the average US tariff up to about 15%
overall. Okay. But he's also in his
erratic way that he's rolled out his
tariffs and kept changing them almost on
a daily basis. He's hammering uh he's
pounding he's he's shredding our trade
relations with with both allies and
competitors. And you know back in 1945
when we created this global system the
United States was the last man standing.
You know, there were four basic
industrial centers in the world. You
know, Europe was ravaged. Russia was was
in ruins. Japan was a smoldering ruin.
We were the last man standing. We
produced about 50 to 60% of the world's
industrial output. So back then when we
said this is the international order,
that was it. If you wanted to trade, you
wanted to deal, you wanted to borrow
money, you had to come to us. But now
the United States is only 20% of the the
world economy and that means there's
another 88% out there and that's lots of
room for people to trade with each
other. And you know I'm sure John is
following the news as you do. You've
noticed the proliferation of trade
agreements that are taking place around
the world. Canada's trade deal with
China. Britain is going to get its trade
deal. The EU has signed a trade
agreement with Moser. the the the
southern cone of Latin America. India is
trying concluding a a major trade deal
with the European Union. There are all
trade deals around the world in which
the world is trading with each other and
leaving us out because we are erratic.
And by the time this is done, there are
going to be two consequences. One, our
access to international markets will be
reduced. And two, as nations begin
trading in non-doll denominated
transactions,
the dollar is going to decline as the
global reserve currency. I believe it's
already gone down from something like
about 70% plus of international
transaction to about the mid50s. Okay,
that's a pretty rapid decline. Okay, and
if it keeps declining, what's going to
happen is the dollar will lose its
preeminence as the global reserve
currency. And that'll mean the cost of
our debt, the cost of our borrowing, and
indeed the costs of goods in American
stores is going to go up. It's going to
creep up constantly. And that's going to
have a delotterious impact on the
quality of life for American, you know,
minimum wage workers, which are a large
portion of our population. Because the
grand American bargain is we pay you
lousy wages, but you have access to
cheap goods. You can go to Walmart and
you can get your food and your clothes
and your appliances cheap, right? Okay.
[clears throat]
And we can do that because you know we
are the world's pre-minent power. The
almighty dollar allows us to buy from
the world market dirt cheap. All right.
Well, that will be over.
>> Yeah.
>> And that'll mean that the lousy wages
will remain, but the goods will no
longer be affordable and people will
hurt. There will be suffering and it's
going to happen rather quickly. Folks,
if you've been waiting for the right
time to stock up, this is it. Right now,
All Family Pharmacy is running a
President's Day sale with 47%
off Ivormectin, Meendazol, and
hydroxychloricquin.
These are some of the most requested
medications for people who want to stay
prepared, have options at home, and not
be stuck scrambling when there's a
storm, shipping delays, or doctor
appointments are all booked out. And
this is why all family pharmacy is
different. You don't have to fight with
your doctor, sit in a waiting room, or
deal with insurance. You simply go
online, fill out a quick medical form,
and one of their licensed doctors
reviews your request, writes the
prescription, and your medication ships
straight to your door. It's simple, it's
straightforward, and no coupon is
required. The sale runs through February
17th, and once it ends, the price goes
right back up. So, if you've been
thinking about stocking up, don't wait.
Go to allfamilyfarm pharmacy.com/joh
and take advantage of the 47% off
President's Day sale before Tuesday,
February 17th. I wanted to ask you if I
could one last question. You've actually
touched on it a little bit, but I wanted
to come back to it and and that is the
that is the current state of NATO and
and the continued efficacy of NATO. I
don't understand what the strategy is at
the White House to attack NATO to
threaten essentially to invade another
NATO country or to take it by force uh
to to force you know economic u uh
benefits out of it rare earth medals or
whatever they happen to be. I don't
understand if this is just Donald Trump
being Donald Trump or if there is some
grander
policy at play here that that we just
don't get. What do you think and and
what do you think the lasting effect
will be on NATO?
>> Sure. Uh the Trump's antagonism towards
NATO is is is well documented. It was
very clear in his first term in which he
uh he he strained the alliance. Uh to
give Trump his credit, he was right
about one thing that Europe taking
basically a free ride on American
defense and not maintaining its defense
industries and its defense capacity
given the fact that Russia Putin was on
its borders and and Ukraine is only the
first target. Let's let's think about
Estonia, Latia, Lithuania,
and [clears throat] there's always
Poland and we can go on. Um, you know,
so that seems in retrospect that was
judicious on his part. Actually, that
was one of the things Trump got right.
Okay. Um and um uh so so now that that
NATO is
aware of the threat that it's facing and
is now voting
pretty much right across the board
reason amount for their own defense. Um,
NATO has been revitalized
in part from Trump's pressures, in part
from the reality of of Putin's ongoing
invasion of of Ukraine and and the the
horror show that that presents in
European news on a on an absolute on a
daily basis. Okay. So, so, so NATO has
been revitalized um by by the Ukraine
war. Moreover, um you know, uh Ukraine
was the kind of thing that NATO was
created for, right? It was designed to
secure Europe against Soviet pressure.
Well, now that's Russian pressure. So it
circumstances and treaty came together
perfectly and NATO responded quite
effectively and it its bonds were
strengthened. But but that but Trump's
antagonism towards NATO is beyond the
rational. It's I think first of all he
doesn't like collaborative
uh ventures of any sort or kind. He
doesn't like the United Nations, right?
He wants his board of peace in which
he's the chairman. He gets to pick the
successor. The billion dollar donations
are going to go into his bank account
some place under his control. And that's
what he wants. He wants he has this this
uni polar uniersonal vision of himself
as a leader both domestically and
particularly internationally because you
know he's allowed to to play
greater power exercise greater
individual power internationally than he
can domestically here he's constrained
by elections courts congress civic
protests all the rest internationally no
so he can have his vision of grandeur
and glory on an international stage. And
he just doesn't like collaborative
ventures of any sort. You know, he's
taken us out of dozens of international
organizations. He's weakened the US
position and presence in the UN and
again NATO as well. All right. So that's
pretty consistent with his personality
and consistent with his policy.
Moreover, again, it fits with Donald
Trump's trinental policy. If you look at
the things he's done, claiming Canada is
a 51st straight, claiming Greenland as
US sovereign territory, demanding the
return of the Panama Canal. In his first
State of the nation address last year, I
mean, he said it that we are going to
reclaim the Panama Canal. All right. um
you know that that he's moving to
establish the US as the unchallenged
hegeimon the unchallenged suzarin over
the western hemisphere right and that's
you know and then let Putin play around
in Europe and let Xi Jinping play around
in Asia and maybe we'll fight over the
Pacific you know but that that's that's
that's that appears to be if you look at
the formal written strategy you look at
the things he says the offhand comments
the policy initiative makes it all comes
together into a a pretty coherent
vision.
>> Professor Alfred McCoy, thank you very
much for enlightening us. I I really
learned a lot. Thanks for being with us.
We appreciate your time.
>> Thank you, John.
>> Thank you.